<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Make More Machines - publications</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.agapow.net/feeds/publications.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.agapow.net/</id><updated>2017-06-23T12:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Tree balance signature of mass extinction is erased by continued evolution ...</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/publications/plosone-2017-tree-balance-erased/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-23T12:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-23T12:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Paul Agapow</name></author><id>tag:www.agapow.net,2017-06-23:/publications/plosone-2017-tree-balance-erased/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kind and duration of phylogenetic topological “signatures” left in the wake
of macroevolutionary events remain poorly understood. To this end, we examined a
broad range of simulated phylogenies generated using trait-biased, heritable
speciation probabilities and mass extinction that could be either random or
selective on trait value, but …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kind and duration of phylogenetic topological “signatures” left in the wake
of macroevolutionary events remain poorly understood. To this end, we examined a
broad range of simulated phylogenies generated using trait-biased, heritable
speciation probabilities and mass extinction that could be either random or
selective on trait value, but also using background extinction and
diversity-dependence to constrain clade sizes. In keeping with prior results,
random mass extinction increased imbalance of clades that recovered to
pre-extinction size, but was a relatively weak effect. Mass extinction that was
selective on trait values tended to produce clades of similar or greater balance
compared to random extinction or controls. Allowing evolution to continue past
the point of clade-size recovery resulted in erosion and eventual erasure of
this signal, with all treatments converging on similar values of imbalance,
except for very intense extinction regimes targeted at taxa with high speciation
rates. Return to a more balanced state with extended post-extinction evolution
was also associated with loss of the previous phylogenetic root in most
treatments. These results further demonstrate that while a mass extinction event
can produce a recognizable phylogenetic signal, its effects become increasingly
obscured the further an evolving clade gets from that event, with any sharp
imbalance due to unrelated evolutionary factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yang, Agapow, Yedid (2017) &amp;quot;The tree balance signature of mass extinction is erased by continued evolution in clades of constrained size with trait-dependent speciation&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;PLoS ONE&lt;/em&gt; 12(6): e0179553.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0179553"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0179553&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="publication"></category><category term="macroevolution"></category><category term="phylogeny"></category><category term="extinction"></category></entry><entry><title>Fishpathogens.eu/noda</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/publications/jfishdis-2015-v38-db/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-11-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-11-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul Agapow</name></author><id>tag:www.agapow.net,2015-11-01:/publications/jfishdis-2015-v38-db/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Viral nervous necrosis (VNN) is a severe neuropathological disease affecting a broad variety of finfish species worldwide. The causative agent of VNN is a small virus with a bi-segmented RNA genome known as betanodavirus. At least four genotypes with distinct, but yet insufficiently characterized, epidemiological features are recognized. The …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Viral nervous necrosis (VNN) is a severe neuropathological disease affecting a broad variety of finfish species worldwide. The causative agent of VNN is a small virus with a bi-segmented RNA genome known as betanodavirus. At least four genotypes with distinct, but yet insufficiently characterized, epidemiological features are recognized. The infectivity of VNN to an increasing number of host species, its wide geographical extent and its economical and ecological impact, justify the importance of collating as much molecular data as possible for tracing the origin of an isolate, and highlight the need for a freely accessible tool for epidemiological and molecular data sharing and consultation. For this purpose, we established a web-based betanodavirus database using the www.FishPathogens.eu platform, with the aim of collecting molecular and epidemiological information on VNN virus, with relevance to its control, management and research study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mikkelsen, Panzarin, Jonstrup, Bigarré, Baud, Gray, Agapow, Olesen (2015). Fishpathogens.eu/noda: a free and handy online platform for Betanodavirus targeted research and data sharing. Journal of Fish Diseases, v38:755-760. DOI: 10.1111/jfd.12378&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="database"></category><category term="fish"></category><category term="disease"></category></entry><entry><title>Micro-evolutionary diversification among Indian Ocean parrots</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/publications/ibis-vX-2015-parrots/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-10-01T12:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-10-01T12:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Paul Agapow</name></author><id>tag:www.agapow.net,2015-10-01:/publications/ibis-vX-2015-parrots/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost 90% of global bird extinctions have occurred on islands. The loss of endemic species from island systems can dramatically alter evolutionary trajectories of insular species biodiversity, resulting in a loss of evolutionary diversity important for species adaptation to changing environments. The Western Indian Ocean islands have been the …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost 90% of global bird extinctions have occurred on islands. The loss of endemic species from island systems can dramatically alter evolutionary trajectories of insular species biodiversity, resulting in a loss of evolutionary diversity important for species adaptation to changing environments. The Western Indian Ocean islands have been the scene of evolution for a large number of endemic parrots. Since their discovery in the 16th century, many of these parrots have become extinct or have declined in numbers. Alongside the extinction of species, a number of the Indian Ocean islands have experienced colonization by highly invasive parrots, such as the Ring-necked Parakeet Psittacula krameri. Such extinctions and invasions can, on an evolutionary timescale, drive changes in species composition, genetic diversity and turnover in phylogenetic diversity, all of which can have important impacts on species potential for adaptation to changing environmental and climatic conditions. Using mtDNA cytochrome b data, we resolve the taxonomic placement of three extinct Indian Ocean parrots: the Rodrigues Psittacula exsul, Seychelles Psittacula wardi and Reunion Parakeets Psittacula eques. This case study quantifies how the extinction of these species has resulted in lost historical endemic phylogenetic diversity and reduced levels of species richness, and illustrates how it is being replaced by non-endemic invasive forms such as the Ring-necked Parakeet. Finally, we use our phylogenetic framework to identify and recommend a number of phylogenetically appropriate ecological replacements for the extinct parrots. Such replacements may be introduced once invasive forms have been cleared, to rejuvenate ecosystem function and restore lost phylogenetic diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jackson, Jones, Agapow, Tatayah &amp;amp; Groombridge (2015) &lt;em&gt;Ibis&lt;/em&gt; v157:496-510, doi:10.1111/ibi.12275&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="publication"></category><category term="extinction"></category><category term="conservation"></category><category term="macroevolution"></category></entry><entry><title>Evolutionary Dynamics of Local Pandemic H1N1/2009 Influenza Virus Lineages Revealed by Whole-Genome Analysis</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/publications/jvi-v86-2012-h1n1/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-01T12:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-10-01T12:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Paul Agapow</name></author><id>tag:www.agapow.net,2012-10-01:/publications/jvi-v86-2012-h1n1/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virus gene sequencing and phylogenetics can be used to study the epidemiological dynamics of rapidly evolving viruses. With complete genome data, it becomes possible to identify and trace individual transmission chains of viruses such as influenza virus during the course of an epidemic. Here we sequenced 153 pandemic influenza …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virus gene sequencing and phylogenetics can be used to study the epidemiological dynamics of rapidly evolving viruses. With complete genome data, it becomes possible to identify and trace individual transmission chains of viruses such as influenza virus during the course of an epidemic. Here we sequenced 153 pandemic influenza H1N1/09 virus genomes from United Kingdom isolates from the first (127 isolates) and second (26 isolates) waves of the 2009 pandemic and used their sequences, dates of isola- tion, and geographical locations to infer the genetic epidemiology of the epidemic in the United Kingdom. We demonstrate that the epidemic in the United Kingdom was composed of many cocirculating lineages, among which at least 13 were exclusively or predominantly United Kingdom clusters. The estimated divergence times of two of the clusters predate the detection of pan- demic H1N1/09 virus in the United Kingdom, suggesting that the pandemic H1N1/09 virus was already circulating in the United Kingdom before the first clinical case. Crucially, three clusters contain isolates from the second wave of infections in the United Kingdom, two of which represent chains of transmission that appear to have persisted within the United Kingdom between the first and second waves. This demonstrates that whole-genome analysis can track in fine detail the behavior of individual influ- enza virus lineages during the course of a single epidemic or pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baillie, Galiano, Agapow, et al. (2012). Journal of Virology 86:11-18.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="publication"></category><category term="epidemiology"></category><category term="phylogeny"></category><category term="influenza"></category><category term="h1n1"></category></entry><entry><title>Evolutionary Pathways of the Pandemic Influenza A (H1N1) 2009 in the UK</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/publications/plos-v6-2011-h1n1/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-01T12:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-10-01T12:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Paul Agapow</name></author><id>tag:www.agapow.net,2012-10-01:/publications/plos-v6-2011-h1n1/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emergence of the influenza (H1N1) 2009 virus provided a unique opportunity to study the evolution of a pandemic virus following its introduction into the human population. Virological and clinical surveillance in the UK were comprehensive during the first and second waves of the pandemic in 2009, with extensive …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emergence of the influenza (H1N1) 2009 virus provided a unique opportunity to study the evolution of a pandemic virus following its introduction into the human population. Virological and clinical surveillance in the UK were comprehensive during the first and second waves of the pandemic in 2009, with extensive laboratory confirmation of infection allowing a detailed sampling of representative circulating viruses. We sequenced the complete coding region of the haemagglutinin (HA) segment of 685 H1N1 pandemic viruses selected without bias during two waves of pandemic in the UK (April-December 2009). Phylogenetic analysis showed that although temporal accumulation of amino acid changes was observed in the HA sequences, the overall diversity was less than that typically seen for seasonal influenza A H1N1 or H3N2. There was co-circulation of multiple variants as characterised by signature amino acid changes in the HA. A specific substitution (S203T) became predominant both in UK and global isolates. No antigenic drift occurred during 2009 as viruses with greater than four-fold reduction in their haemagglutination inhibition (HI) titre (‘‘low reactors’’) were detected in a low proportion (3%) and occurred sporadically. Although some limited antigenic divergence in viruses with four-fold reduction in HI titre might be related to the presence of 203T, additional studies are needed to test this hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Galiano M, Agapow P-M, Thompson C, Platt S, Underwood A, et al. (2011) PLoS ONE 6(8): e23779. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0023779&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="publication"></category><category term="epidemiology"></category><category term="phylogeny"></category><category term="influenza"></category><category term="h1n1"></category></entry><entry><title>Evolutionary Pathways of the Pandemic Influenza A (H1N1) 2009 in the UK</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/publications/plos-v6-2011-h1n1%20copy/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-01T12:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-10-01T12:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Paul Agapow</name></author><id>tag:www.agapow.net,2012-10-01:/publications/plos-v6-2011-h1n1 copy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emergence of the influenza (H1N1) 2009 virus provided a unique opportunity to study the evolution of a pandemic virus following its introduction into the human population. Virological and clinical surveillance in the UK were comprehensive during the first and second waves of the pandemic in 2009, with extensive …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emergence of the influenza (H1N1) 2009 virus provided a unique opportunity to study the evolution of a pandemic virus following its introduction into the human population. Virological and clinical surveillance in the UK were comprehensive during the first and second waves of the pandemic in 2009, with extensive laboratory confirmation of infection allowing a detailed sampling of representative circulating viruses. We sequenced the complete coding region of the haemagglutinin (HA) segment of 685 H1N1 pandemic viruses selected without bias during two waves of pandemic in the UK (April-December 2009). Phylogenetic analysis showed that although temporal accumulation of amino acid changes was observed in the HA sequences, the overall diversity was less than that typically seen for seasonal influenza A H1N1 or H3N2. There was co-circulation of multiple variants as characterised by signature amino acid changes in the HA. A specific substitution (S203T) became predominant both in UK and global isolates. No antigenic drift occurred during 2009 as viruses with greater than four-fold reduction in their haemagglutination inhibition (HI) titre (‘‘low reactors’’) were detected in a low proportion (3%) and occurred sporadically. Although some limited antigenic divergence in viruses with four-fold reduction in HI titre might be related to the presence of 203T, additional studies are needed to test this hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Galiano M, Agapow P-M, Thompson C, Platt S, Underwood A, et al. (2011) PLoS ONE 6(8): e23779. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0023779&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="publication"></category><category term="epidemiology"></category><category term="phylogeny"></category><category term="influenza"></category><category term="h1n1"></category></entry><entry><title>Species: demarcation &amp; diversity</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/publications/phylandcons-2005-species-concept/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-01T12:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-10-01T12:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Paul Agapow</name></author><id>tag:www.agapow.net,2012-10-01:/publications/phylandcons-2005-species-concept/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguments about conservation are almost always arguments about species. Lists are compiled of endangered species, conservation schemes are prioritised on how many species are preserved, and legislation is phrased in terms of species. In the political economy of biodiversity, species are the currency. Despite this central role, the very …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguments about conservation are almost always arguments about species. Lists are compiled of endangered species, conservation schemes are prioritised on how many species are preserved, and legislation is phrased in terms of species. In the political economy of biodiversity, species are the currency. Despite this central role, the very term 'species' is deeply ambiguous. Practitioners clash not only over the boundaries of individual species, but also over what 'species' means. Where once ‘the species problem’ referred to the puzzle of how species arose, it now refers to how species can be defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This argument has deep implications for conservation biology. As species definitions (and thus boundaries) shift, species counts may rise and fall. Areas of endemism based on species counts could change, and the con- servation worth of populations with an ambiguous status (such as hybrids and sub-species) will fluctuate based on their taxonomic rank. Given such doubt, how precise are our current understandings of species numbers and identity? Are these estimates good enough for conservation practice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P-M Agapow (2005). Species: demarcation and diversity. In Phylogeny and Conservation (eds. A Purvis, JL Gittleman and TM Brooks). Cambridge (UK): Cambridge University Press&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="publication"></category><category term="conservation"></category><category term="species"></category><category term="phylogeny"></category></entry><entry><title>Conservation genetics: from species to habitats</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/publications/bi-v47-2001-conservation-genetics/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul Agapow</name></author><id>tag:www.agapow.net,2010-01-01:/publications/bi-v47-2001-conservation-genetics/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conservation genetics - and indeed conservation in general - falls into the two broad areas of the identification and preservation of (1) endangered species and (2) habitats with high biodiversity. Most research has been towards the first aim, with hard-won findings on the importance of genetic variation in population management, but …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conservation genetics - and indeed conservation in general - falls into the two broad areas of the identification and preservation of (1) endangered species and (2) habitats with high biodiversity. Most research has been towards the first aim, with hard-won findings on the importance of genetic variation in population management, but genetics promises to be at least as important in the second aim. To this end, molecular phylogenies have long been proposed as an important approach that can capture conservation worth and evolutionary distinctiveness better than simple species richness and avoid common problems in defining species identity and boundaries. Progressively faster and cheaper DNA sequencing and the rise of DNA barcoding are making the phylogenetic approach to habitat conservation widely applicable. Barcoding was seen initially solely as a means to species discovery and to species identification, but it now holds promise as a resource-efficient means of rapidly estimating the evolutionary history preserved by different sets of reserves. Initial indications are that biodiversity assessment, using the short cox1 sequence standard for barcoding animals, reliably reflects the picture from longer sequences. The phylogenetic approach, assisted by barcoding, not only infers evolutionary history but also in synergy with morphology will speed species discovery and the subsequent expansion of general biological knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crozier, Agapow, Smith (2009) &amp;quot;Conservation Genetics: from species to habitat&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;Biol Int&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;47&lt;/strong&gt;:73-79&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="publication"></category><category term="conservation"></category><category term="phylogeny"></category><category term="barcodes"></category></entry><entry><title>The impact of species concept on biodiversity studies</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/publications/qrb-v79-2004-species-concept/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2005-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul Agapow</name></author><id>tag:www.agapow.net,2005-01-01:/publications/qrb-v79-2004-species-concept/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Species are defined using a variety of different operational techniques. While discussion of the various methodologies has previously been restricted mostly to taxonomists, the demarcation of species is also crucial for conservation biology. Unfortunately, different methods of diagnosing species can arrive at different entities. Most prominently, it is widely …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Species are defined using a variety of different operational techniques. While discussion of the various methodologies has previously been restricted mostly to taxonomists, the demarcation of species is also crucial for conservation biology. Unfortunately, different methods of diagnosing species can arrive at different entities. Most prominently, it is widely thought that use of a phylogenetic species concept may lead to recognition of a far greater number of much less inclusive units. As a result, studies of the same group of organisms can produce not only different species identities but also different species range and number of individuals. To assess the impact of different definitions on conservation issues, we collected instances from the literature where a group of organisms was categorized both under phylogenetic and nonphylogenetic concepts. Our results show a marked difference, with surveys based on a phylogenetic species concept showing more species (48%) and an associated decrease in population size and range. We discuss the serious consequences of this trend for conservation, including an apparent change in the number of endangered species, potential political fallout, and the difficulty of deciding what should be conserved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P-M Agapow, OR Bininda-Emonds, K Crandall,  JL Gittleman, G Mace, J Marshall and A Purvis (2004). The Impact of Species Concept on Biodiversity. Q. Rev. Biol. 79:161-179.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="publication"></category><category term="species"></category><category term="phylogeny"></category><category term="biodiversity"></category><category term="conservation"></category></entry><entry><title>Indices of multilocus linkage disequilibrium</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/publications/molecol-v1-2001-multilocus/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2002-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2002-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul Agapow</name></author><id>tag:www.agapow.net,2002-01-01:/publications/molecol-v1-2001-multilocus/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linkage disequilibrium is an ubiquitous biological phenomenon. However a common metric for disequilibrium — the index of association or IA – is dependent on sample size. In this paper we present a modification of IA that removes this dependency. This method has been implemented in a software package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agapow &amp;amp; Burt …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linkage disequilibrium is an ubiquitous biological phenomenon. However a common metric for disequilibrium — the index of association or IA – is dependent on sample size. In this paper we present a modification of IA that removes this dependency. This method has been implemented in a software package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agapow &amp;amp; Burt (2001) &lt;em&gt;Molecular Ecology Notes&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;:101–102&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="also-see"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Also see&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/software/multilocus"&gt;Multilocus (software)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="publication"></category><category term="genetics"></category><category term="disequilibrium"></category></entry><entry><title>Nonrandom Extinction and the Loss of Evolutionary History</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/publications/sci-v288-2000-nonrandom-extinction/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2001-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2001-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul Agapow</name></author><id>tag:www.agapow.net,2001-01-01:/publications/sci-v288-2000-nonrandom-extinction/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hierarchical nature of phylogenies means that random extinction of species affects a smaller fraction of higher taxa, and so the total amount of evolutionary history lost may be comparatively slight. However, current extinction risk is not phylogenetically random. We show the potentially severe implications of the clumped nature …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hierarchical nature of phylogenies means that random extinction of species affects a smaller fraction of higher taxa, and so the total amount of evolutionary history lost may be comparatively slight. However, current extinction risk is not phylogenetically random. We show the potentially severe implications of the clumped nature of threat for the loss of biodiversity. An additional 120 avian and mammalian genera are at risk compared with the number predicted under random extinction. We estimate that the prospective extra loss of mammalian evolutionary history alone would be equivalent to losing a monotypic phylum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purvis, Agapow, Gittleman, Mace (2000) &amp;quot;Nonrandom Extinction and the Loss of Evolutionary History&amp;quot;, &lt;strong&gt;288&lt;/strong&gt;:329-330&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="publication"></category><category term="extinction"></category><category term="conservation"></category><category term="macroevolution"></category></entry><entry><title>Towards complete biodiversity assessment: an evaluation of the subterranean bacterial communities in the Oklo region of the sole surviving natural nuclear reactor</title><link href="http://www.agapow.net/publications/femsme-v28-1999-biodiversity-assess/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2000-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2000-01-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul Agapow</name></author><id>tag:www.agapow.net,2000-01-01:/publications/femsme-v28-1999-biodiversity-assess/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groundwater bacterial rRNA sequences extracted from the natural nuclear reactor region of Gabon are used to demonstrate the application of phylogenetic methods to biodiversity assessment. Clones were provisionally placed in 'genera' using either the genus of the closest named EMBL entry, or by grouping clones at least 97.5 …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="abtsract"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abtsract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groundwater bacterial rRNA sequences extracted from the natural nuclear reactor region of Gabon are used to demonstrate the application of phylogenetic methods to biodiversity assessment. Clones were provisionally placed in 'genera' using either the genus of the closest named EMBL entry, or by grouping clones at least 97.5% identical. The community is small, with 24 putative genera under the 'closest-match' criterion and an estimated number of 30.9 (25.8-49.7); estimated genus sample coverage is therefore 78% (48.3-92.8%). There were 36 genera under the 'threshold' criterion, with an estimated number of 87.2 (52.6-193.8), and sample coverage 41.3% (18.6-68.4%) Molecular biodiversity was estimated for all site combinations using genetic diversity (GD: probability of at least two alleles being present in the sequences preserved), and confidence limits derived by standard phylogenetic bootstrap sampling from the sequence dataset. Some combinations with fewer sites preserved GD as well as combinations with larger numbers, although GD is maximised by preserving as many sites as possible depending on choice of site. Some site combinations did not differ significantly in GD preserved, and the conservation value of a site depends on the others selected. The strongest predictor of molecular biodiversity is the observed number of 'closest-match' genera, supporting the higher taxon richness concept for biodiversity. The similarities between sites, and hence the molecular biodiversity characteristics of combinations of them, was associated with similarity in physical characteristics, the availability of organic carbon, and depth below the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crozier, Agapow, Pederson (1999). FEMS Microbial Ecology 28:325-334&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="publication"></category><category term="biodiversity"></category><category term="assessment"></category></entry></feed>